[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-five]
[第二十五集]
Today we are talking about ancient Chinese philosophy.
今天我们讲的是中国古代哲学
It is a question discussed by the academic circles.
是学界讨论的问题
[Hu Shi, styled Shizhi, Professor at Peking University]
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
What you said just now is a political issue,
你刚才说的是政治问题
a matter of political discussion.
是政界讨论的问题
As a student,
作为学生
it's good to take an interest in Shandong's problems.
关心山东的问题这是好事
But can Shandong be returned to China?
但是山东究竟能不能返还中国
This was the issue discussed, studied, and decided
这是巴黎和会政治家们讨论
by the statesmen of the Paris Peace Conference,
和研究决定的问题
and not an issue that we can decide
而不是今天我们在课堂上
in the classroom today.
能够决定的问题
But students believe that it is impossible
可学生认为学术和政治
to completely separate academics and politics.
是不可能完全分离的
As the saying goes, there is no egg under the overturned nest.
所谓覆巢之下焉有完卵
If a country can't even protect its sovereignty,
如果一个国家连主权都保护不了
what's the point of learning?
还有什么学术可言
Exactly.
就是嘛
Isn't this disturbing the classroom order?
这不是扰乱课堂秩序吗
Academic and political issues
学界问题和政界问题
really shouldn't be confused.
的确不该混淆
There is no egg under the overturned nest.
覆巢之下焉有完卵
Students, please be quiet.
同学们请安静
Students!
同学们
Quiet please.
请安静
Student Guo Xingang.
郭心刚同学
You are in class today,
今天你在课堂上
talking endlessly about Shandong's problems.
喋喋不休地讨论山东的问题
Do you find that useful?
你觉得有用吗
The decision on Shandong lies with Wilson.
山东问题的决定权在威尔逊
Not with one of the students.
而不在你一个学生
The students' task is to learn.
学生的任务就是学习
To learn that the best state of mind
学习最好的状态
is a peaceful mind,
就是心静如水
instead of having a deer in your heart.
而不是心怀小鹿
Sir,
先生
there are not many university students in China.
中国的大学生并不多
Even if we don't care about the Shandong issue,
如果连我们都不关心山东问题
Wilson is a foreigner,
他威尔逊一个外国人
why should he care about our Shandong?
凭什么要关心我们的山东
To tie the sovereignty of Shandong
把山东的主权问题
to a foreigner's mouth,
拴在一个外国人的嘴上
students cannot accept that.
学生认为是靠不住的
Excuse me, sir.
先生 对不起
I can't stay calm.
我做不到心静如水
As students, we should concentrate on our studies.
我们是学生就该专心学习
I think Guo is right. Yes.
我觉得老郭说得对 没错
Wilson is a foreigner,
威尔逊一个外国人
why should he care about our Shandong?
凭什么关心我们的山东
We should care about ourselves.
该我们自己关心才是
Time to eat!
吃饭啦
Okay, right away.
好勒 马上
Time to eat.
吃饭
Okay.
好
How is it steamed cornbread again?
怎么又是窝头啊
I have to show movies tonight.
晚上还得放电影
I can't run on this.
这哪儿扛得住啊
I can make abalone and sea cucumber.
鲍鱼海参我能做
Can you afford that?
你吃得起吗
These days,
这些天
in addition to the dozen people in the group,
除了包伙的那十几个人以外
there are no guests at all.
一个客人都没有
Did I make this steamed cornbread
就这窝头
or borrow it from outside?
还是我从外头赊的
Don't you like to eat?
你爱吃不吃
Comrade Yu Shewei,
俞社委同志
why are we just eating steamed cornbread here?
怎么就咱们几个在这儿啃窝头
Where are the other comrades?
其他同志呢
Just as I was preparing for the evening meeting
我正好准备晚上开会的时候
telling everyone about it.
跟大家说一下
Ge Xiumei from our screening group
那个我们放映组的葛秀梅
has retired from the club,
已经退社
leaving a letter, and has returned to Tianjin today.
留下一封信 今天已经回天津了
How can there be so many quitters in only one month?
怎么才一个月就有逃兵啊
Then there are a few comrades
那还有几个同志呢
who will not also quit the club, right?
不会也退社了吧
Guo is busy with the petition group.
老郭忙活请愿团的事呢
[Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
Bai Lan will not come back when she goes out as a tutor.
白兰出去当家教 就不回来了
Distribute these.
把这分一下啊
Okay.
好
I think our mutual aid society should be reorganized.
我觉得咱们互助社应该整顿了
Regarding this petition group,
这请愿团的事
I think it's more important than our mutual aid society.
就比咱们互助社的事重要
You can eat out when you go out to work.
外出打工就可以下馆子
When the family comes, they can go out and enjoy it.
家里人来了就可以出去享受
Is this still communism?
这还是共产主义吗
When joining the society, didn't we agree
入社的时候大家不说好了
to share weal and woe as a family?
同甘共苦 亲如一家的呀
How come there are privileges and differences now?
怎么现在就出现特权跟差别了
The most critical question now
现在最关键的问题
is to make money.
就是挣钱
Since we started the club, we have been unable to make ends meet.
咱们开社以来一直都是入不敷出
Now we're running out of money.
现在家底都快花光了
I agree with Comrade Yannian.
我同意延年同志的意见啊
The biggest problem we face now
我们现在面临最大的问题
is the problem of survival.
就是生存的问题
Three work-study groups
三个勤工组
have to come up with a better way.
都必须要拿出更好的办法来才行
Brother Guo said
郭大哥说了
to let them come to our place to package meals.
让他们来咱们这儿包伙
and "New Youth" magazine revenue
还有《新青年》杂志的酬劳
has also come down.
也已经下来了
It's all confiscated.
都归公充社了
This comrade Guo Xingang is sick and tired at ordinary times.
这个郭心刚同志 平时病厌厌的
Not active in group activities.
参加集体活动也不积极
The mention of Qingdao is like having chicken blood.
这一提青岛就跟打了鸡血似的
What does he care about chicken blood and cow blood?
管他打什么鸡血牛血呀
Having an income is the key.
创收是关键
If you don't earn money, you won't be able to eat.
再不创收 窝窝头都吃不上了
I'm a chef.
我这个大厨啊
It's time to wash and sleep.
也就该洗洗睡了
I have discussed everything with Comrade Yi.
我跟易同志都商量好了
Go to their school tomorrow to find the clerk.
明天就去他们学校找他们斋夫
Give him ten percent more commission.
多给他一成的提成
See if he can help us get some business.
看他能不能帮咱们揽点生意
This is unfair competition.
这是不正当竞争啊
It's survival of the fittest.
物竞天择 适者生存
Don't care so much.
顾不了那么多了
Then I'll go with you tomorrow.
那明天我也跟你们去吧
If it were not for Xie Wanying
要不是人家谢婉莹
mobilizing girls from all schools
发动各个学校女生
to give us charity,
对我们的施舍
our screening group would have closed down.
我们放映组早歇业了
I can't stand being a seven-foot man.
堂堂七尺男儿我可受不了这个
Yannian,
延年
I think we need to find a time
我觉得我们有必要找个时间
to discuss the articles of association.
讨论修改一下互助社章程了
Okay, I think it's very important.
行 我看非常有必要
That's let's do it.
那就说好了
Go on.
走
Brother Mao,
毛大哥
I haven't seen you for so long.
这么长时间没见你
We all thought you were back in Hunan.
我们都还以为你回湖南了
Actually, it's been half a month,
其实这半个月啊
and I've did two things.
我就干了两件事情
What's the first?
这第一呢
With the help of Mr. Zhang Shizhao
是在章士钊先生的帮助下
that we sent the first batch of students
把我们湖南赴法的
from our Hunan to France.
第一批学生给送走了
The second thing,
这第二件事情呢
was following Mr. Li Dazhao
就是跟着李大钊先生
to Changxindian several times.
去了好几次长辛店
Every day, coming home at night.
每天都是夜出夜归的
I really don't have time to see you.
实在没有时间看你们
I said I haven't seen you for half a month.
我说这半个月没见着你
Why do you look tired?
怎么看你有些疲惫呢
Actually,
其实啊
I'm here for one more thing.
我这次来还有一件事情
I'm leaving tomorrow,
我明天就要走了
back to Hunan.
回湖南了
You're going back?
你要回去啦
Yes.
是啊
In the blink of an eye, more than half a year.
这一转眼半年多
Things in Beijing have been settled.
北京的事情解决了
But what about the Xinmin Society?
可是新民学会那边呢
There are still many things to deal with.
还有很多的事情要处理
During my time in Beijing,
在北京的时候呢
I am very grateful to your brothers for taking care of me.
承蒙你们兄弟俩对我的照顾
So I still
所以我呢
want to specially
还是要特意
politely decline.
辞谢一下的
Brother Runzhi,
润之兄
that's so kind of you.
你太客气了
It's rare to get to know you.
能结识你挺难得的
And from your viewpoint,
而且从你的身上啊
I can see something that I can't see in Beijing.
能看到一种在北京看不到的东西
How do you say this?
此话怎讲啊
I don't know exactly.
我也说不太清楚
I always feel that only you
总觉得只有在你的身上
[Mao Zedong, styled Runzhi, Peking University Library Assistant]
[毛泽东 字 润之 北京大学图书馆助理员]
can see what is really happening
才能看到什么是真正地
to the people.
走向大众
Actually,
其实啊
I should thank you both.
我应该谢谢你们两个
Look,
你看啊
you guys are working to support yourselves.
你们靠自己打工养活自己
This
这个啊
is a practical approach to the public.
就是切实地走向大众
But we continue to do it anymore.
但是我们快办不下去了
We are going to fail.
我们要失败了
Qiaonian, come.
乔年 来
I think
我觉得吧
failure is not so terrible.
失败并不可怕
Why not start all over again?
大不了从头再来嘛
Maybe
说不准
we can find a new road again.
还能再找出一条新的道路呢
Isn't that right, Yannian?
是不是啊 延年
This mutual aid society has been running for almost two months.
这互助社快办了两个月了
I always feel that there is something missing.
我总觉得还缺点什么
It seems to have only one shell and no soul.
它好像只有一个壳没有魂
This road still won't work.
这条路还是行不通啊
I wish to cross the Yellow River,
欲渡黄河
yet ice blocks the river.
冰塞川
I wish to climb Taihang,
将登太行
yet snow covers the mountain.
雪满山
Hard is the journey.
行路难
Many roads divided,
多歧路
which to take?
今安在
Yannian,
延年
Qiaonian.
乔年
I think,
我觉得
although the road is long,
路虽漫漫
but Beijing
但是北京
has a kingly spirit.
自有一股王气在
Mr. Zhongfu,
仲甫先生
Mr. Shouchang,
守常先生
their claims
他们的主张
are a deafening,
就是振聋发聩
kingly energy that cleanses the heaven and earth,
荡涤乾坤的王气
and
而且呢
they are also the spiritual leaders and mentors
他们又是我们新青年的
of our new youth.
精神领袖和导师
And the new youth of our time
而我们当代的新青年
is to connect this kingly spirit with the earthly spirit.
就是要把这种王气和地气给接起来
In practice,
在现实中
searching up and down
上下求索
for a new way out
为天下找到一条
for the world.
新的出路
Each age brings forth
江山代有
a new genius on this noble land.
才人出
Their poems and articles will be known for ages to come.
各领风骚数百年
Brother Runzhi,
润之兄
to save the country and the people,
为了救国救民
I am willing to walk with you,
我愿与你同行
to work together,
一起努力
to cheer together.
一起加油
A long wind
长风破浪
will break the waves.
会有时
Setting sail
直挂云帆
and crossing the sea.
济沧海
Encourage each other!
共勉
Runzhi,
润之啊
you're going back this time,
你这次回去
what are you going to do?
准备做些什么呀
I want to know our China well
我想好好地了解一下我们的中国
and see what our country lacks.
看看我们的国家到底缺的是什么
I can give you the answer to your question right now.
你这个问题我现在就可以给你答案
Science and democracy.
科学与民主啊
What China lacks most now
现在中国最缺的
are these two things.
就是这两样东西
Well said, sir.
先生说得好
Precisely said.
说得准确
But,
不过
I still want to know about it.
我还是想了解一下
A country like ours,
像我们这样一个大多数
where most of the people are farmers and illiterate.
都是农民和文盲的国家
What is it like?
到底怎么样
Only then
才能走得通
can we walk the path where science and democracy converge.
科学和民主相交融的路
That's a good question.
这个问题问得好
Asked well.
问得深
I recently wrote an article.
我最近写了一篇
on "Youth and the Countryside".
《青年与农村》的文章
I'm also trying to explore this question.
也在努力探讨这个问题
Young people dare to think and do.
年轻人敢想敢干
Worth advocating.
值得提倡
China's development
中国要发展
must be supported by the introduction
必须要引进最先进的
of the most advanced theories.
理论做支撑
Yes, sir.
是的 先生
Sir,
先生
I have a question
我有一个问题
I've always wanted to ask you.
一直想请教您
Go on.
你说
Do you really think
您真的认为
the fundamental problem of China
中国的根本问题
is a problem of backward cultural traditions?
是落后的文化传统问题吗
No.
非也
It is not culture that lags China behind.
中国落后的不是文化
It's the lack of theories to guide the sustainable development of society.
是缺乏指导社会持续发展的理论
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Dean of Liberal Arts at Peking University]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学文科学长]
Scientific theories.
科学理论
Then why did you two gentlemen
那二位先生
use so much energy
为什么要用这么大的精力
shaking down old culture?
去抖击旧文化呢
Because it suppresses and hinders
因为它压制和阻碍了
the birth of science and democracy.
科学和民主的生成啊
More importantly, some people
更重要的是有些人
think of it as
要把它奉为
as a guiding ideology to save the country.
救国治国的指导思想
Unless you knock it down,
你不打倒它
new theories cannot stand.
新的理论就无法立足
As the saying goes, if you don't break it, you can't build it.
所谓不破不立
That's the truth.
就是这个道理
Then it seems
那看来
You two gentlemen are not trying to reject
二位先生并非要全盘
traditional culture in its entirety.
否定传统文化
Of course not.
那当然不是
No one can deny the profundity
中国传统文化博大精深
of Chinese traditional culture.
谁也否定不了
In time,
假以时日
the country will be peaceful.
国泰民安了
I'd love to
我倒很乐意
spend my old age in a pile of old papers.
在故纸堆里面安度晚年
What a pleasant thing that is!
那是一件多么惬意的事情啊
My wish is surprisingly consistent with yours.
我跟你的愿望出奇地一致
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library]
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
So Runzhi,
所以润之
it is imperative
当务之急
to find a new scientific theory
是为了我们中国
for our China.
寻找新的科学理论
Are you really not going to work-study in France?
你真不打算去法国勤工俭学了
I still don't want to go abroad.
我还是不想出国
If I really want to go abroad,
如果真的要出国
then I'd like to go to Russia.
我倒是想去俄国
You want to go to Russia,
你要去俄国
then you should ask Shouchang more.
那你可要多请教守常啊
He is a big fan of Russia now.
他现在是俄国迷
Leninism
对列宁的主义
can be described as a few treasures.
可谓是如数家珍
But now,
但是现在啊
I still want to have a good look
我还是想好好地看看
of our own China.
我们自己的中国
Good.
好
We will meet again.
我们还会再见
Next time,
等下次
I want to listen to your views on China.
我要好好听听你对中国的见解
Then,
那
gentlemen, please stay.
二位先生请留步
I shall leave now.
学生告辞了
It's a deal.
就这么定了
You will preside over the meeting later.
一会儿会议你主持
Okay, I'll host it.
好 我来主持
Comrades,
同志们
let's all put aside our work.
大家把手里的活儿都放一放
Let's have a meeting.
我们开个会
We're all here.
都到齐了啊
Comrades, today's meeting is very important
同志们 今天这个会议很重要
[Yu Xiusong, Student at Zhejiang First Provincial Normal School]
[俞秀松 浙江省立第一师范学生]
There are thirteen original members of our work-study mutual aid society.
我们工读互助社原始成员十三人
Two people have left the club.
已有两人退社
Eleven people still present,
应到十一人
including Comrade Guo Xingang who verbally proposed to quit the club,
包括口头提出退社的郭心刚同志
are also attending the meeting tonight.
也参加了今晚的会议
There are three agendas for our meeting today.
我们今天会议一共有三项议程
First, each work-study group reports its work.
一是各个勤工小组汇报工作
Second, discuss amending the articles of association of mutual aid society.
二是讨论修改互助社章程
Third, study the future work.
三是研究今后的工作
Let's move on to the first agenda of the meeting.
下面我们进行会议第一项议程
Every group must reports its work.
各小组汇报工作
Shi Cuntong, let's talk about yours first.
施存统 你先来说说吧
I have nothing to say.
我没什么好说的
[Shi Cuntong, Student at Zhejiang First Provincial Normal School]
[施存统 浙江省立第一师范学生]
The laundry group's business has been revoked.
洗衣组的业务已经被吊销了
What about the laundry group? It doesn't exist anymore.
洗衣组呢已经不存在了
As team leader, I apologize to all of you.
我作为组长 向各位道歉
The report is over.
汇报完了
Since the opening of the frugal canteen,
俭洁食堂开业以来
it has been in a state of loss and semi-loss.
一直处于亏损和半亏损的状态
Initial funds are running out.
启动资金也快用完了
At this rate,
照这样下去
we have one week at most.
最多再维持一周
Finished.
说完了
Our screening group was also disbanded today.
我们放映组也于今天解散了
The reason is that for two months,
原因是两个月以来
only three films can be shown.
只有三部影片可以放映
All the schools that can show it have finished showing it.
能放映的学校都已经放映完了
There's no audience.
没有观众
The reason we can hold up to today
我们之所以能撑到今天
is completely dependent on female students
完全是靠女同学
to introduce us to personal connections.
给我们介绍的人脉支持
I don't think it's a business,
我觉得这不是一种经营
but a kind of charity.
而是一种施舍
I couldn't stand it, so it was dismissed.
我忍受不了 所以解散了
I'm done.
我说完了
Well.
好
The three teams have finished reporting.
三个小组汇报完毕
Let's start the second agenda.
现在开始第二项议程
Yannian.
延年
Two out of three work-study groups closed down.
三个勤工小组倒闭了两个
There's another one that can barely last a week.
还有一个只能勉强维持一周
I don't think it is necessary
我认为已经没有必要
that we move on to the second agenda.
再进行第二项议程了
We should admit that we failed.
应该承认 我们失败了
We should announce it fair and square
我们应该正大光明地宣布
that the first experimental group of the mutual aid society
工读互助社第一实验小组
will dissolve.
解散
Comrade Guo Xingang,
郭心刚同志
mutual aid societies are not dissolved.
互助社解不解散
First you have to solve the problem, right?
首先得解决问题吧
We can't just become
我们不能糊里糊涂地
an anarchist experiment in a muddle.
就当了无政府主义的试验品啊
What's not clear?
有什么不清楚的
Anarchism is not for us.
无政府主义不适合我们
That's the conclusion.
这就是结论
I disagree with you.
我不同意你的看法
Do I think anarchism won't work?
我看不是无政府主义行不通
But we didn't understand it at all.
而是我们根本没有搞清楚
What is anarchism?
什么才是无政府主义的
It's principle of mutual aid theory.
互助论原则
Well.
好啊
Then please, you unfilial gentleman,
那就请你这位非孝先生
let me ask you,
来给大家讲讲
what is the principle of mutual aid?
什么是互助论的原则
Very well.
好
First of all, the first principle of mutual aid theory
首先 互助论的第一个原则
is communism.
就是共产
No one in the mutual aid society
互助社内任何人
may keep private property.
都不得保留私人财产
But look at our club.
可是你看看我们这个社吧
When Yi Qunxian first contributed
当易群先把自己的衣服
her clothes to the group.
贡献给大家的时候
What did she get?
得到的是什么
Sarcasm and ridicule.
得到的是讽刺和嘲笑
When people are penniless,
当大多数人已经身无分文的时候
some people have small coffers.
有的人还有小金库
When most people
当大多数人
have disassociated themselves from family relationships,
已经脱离家庭关系的时候
some people have dinner with their families.
有些人却可以和家人去吃饭
Of course, I don't mean anything against anyone.
当然我没有针对谁的意思
I just wanted to say
我只是想说
is that this remnant of private ownership
正是这种私有制残余
is corrupting our mutual aid society
腐蚀了我们的互助社
and causing a disharmony between us,
使我们之间出现了感情不融洽
mutual suspicion,
互相猜疑
and spiritual disconnection among us.
和精神散的现象
I disagree with you.
我不同意你的观点
I don't think the reason why the mutual aid society can't go on.
我认为 互助社之所以办不下去
It's because in this society,
是因为这个社会
there is no condition for the free development of individuals.
没有提供给个人自由发展的条件
In other words,
也就是说
personal labor is not enough to maintain oneself
个人劳动不足以维护
when it comes to individual interests.
个体利益的时候
Mutual aid is just a fantasy.
互助它只是一种空想
I don't agree to dissolve the mutual aid society.
我不同意解散互助社
The reason why I ran away from home and came here
我从家里跑出来来到这儿
is to pursue freedom.
就是为了追求自由
It's a little bitter to be a mutual aid society member,
是 互助社是苦了一点
but it gave me freedom.
但是它给了我自由
Especially,
特别是
especially the freedom to pursue love.
特别是给了我追求爱情的自由
Sister Qun, who are you in love with?
群先姐姐 那你到底爱上谁了
Okay, I'll take this opportunity today
好 我今天就趁这个机会
to have a bold announcement.
大胆地宣布
I have fallen in love with
我爱上了
Comrade He Mengxiong.
何孟雄同志
Sorry, Comrade He Mengxiong.
对不起 何孟雄同志
[He Mengxiong, Visiting student at Peking University]
[何孟雄 北京大学旁听生]
Sorry, Comrade Yi.
对不起 易同志
I already have someone I love.
我已经有心爱的人了
What are you nervous about?
你紧张什么呀
You can like others.
你可以去喜欢别人
But it doesn't affect my feelings for you.
但是并不影响我对你的感情
In that case,
既然这样
I don't want to hide my feelings anymore.
我也不想隐瞒我的感情了
I declare that at least until now,
我宣布 至少到现在为止
I think Comrade Yi Qunxian
我觉得易群先同志
is still really cute.
还是十分可爱的
Good!
好
Thank you.
谢谢
Comrades, we're off topic.
同志们 跑题了
Let's get down to business now.
我们现在言归正题
The problem we are facing is
我们现在面临的问题是
that hard work is no longer enough
勤工已经不能维持
to keep the mutual aid society afloat.
互助社的生存了
What are we going to do now?
我们现在要怎么办
There is no alternative but dissolution.
除了解散别无他法
I don't agree to dissolve the mutual aid society.
我不同意解散互助社
If the mutual aid society is disbanded,
互助社解散了
won't I have to go back to my old life?
我岂不是又要回到原来的生活
I disagree.
我不同意
Do you disagree?
你不同意
Then come up with something.
那你拿出办法来
What can I do?
我能有什么办法
Unless my dad comes to sponsor us.
除非让我爸过来赞助咱们
Do you agree?
你们同意吗
What can you do about it?
你这算什么办法呀
Let's be parasites.
让我们当寄生虫啊
Then I can't help it.
那我就没有办法了
Yannian.
延年
You are the social committee and have a special status.
你是社委 又有特殊身份
At the end of the day, we people
说到底我们这些人
are all influenced by "New Youth"
都是受了《新青年》的影响
to find a new way out.
才跑出来寻找新出路的
Tell us all about it.
你给我们大家说说吧
Very well.
好
Comrades.
各位同志
I am one of the initiators
我是我们这个工读互助社
of the first experimental group of our work-study mutual aid society.
第一实验小组的发起人之一
Now this experiment has failed.
现在这个实验失败了
I am responsible.
我有责任
I'm sorry everyone.
我对不起大家
Yannian, don't do this.
延年 你别这样
It's not your responsibility.
这件事不是你的责任
First of all, I want to make a statement.
首先我要声明一点
I'm not a believer in Chen Duxiu.
我不是陈独秀的信徒
It is true that I ideologically
诚然我在思想上
agree with the New Culture Movement he advocated.
赞同他提倡的新文化运动
I support his proposal of science and democracy.
我拥护他提出的德先生跟赛先生
But I really don't know
但是我确实不知道
what theory he believes in,
他信仰什么理论
and I am a man of faith,
而我是有信仰的
I respond to Wang Guangqi's call.
我响应王光祈的号召
for this work-study mutual aid society experiment
搞了这个工读互助社实验
because I have great hope for the work-study mutual aid society.
是因为对于工读互助社
I have great hopes
我抱有莫大的希望
I hope that the future society
我希望将来的社会
can also become a work-study society.
也能够成为一个工读互助的社会
But today I have to admit
但是今天我必须得承认
our experiment failed.
我们的实验失败了
What is the reason for the failure?
失败的原因是什么
I haven't figured it out yet.
我一时还没有理清楚
But what I know is
但是我清楚的是
I will never give up
我绝不会因为
my pursuit of the ideal society
一次短暂实验的失败
in my heart
而放弃我对心中
because of the failure of a short experiment.
理想社会的追求
I believe
我相信
everyone here must be like me.
在座各位一定也和我一样
Even if what awaits us in front of us
即使面前等待我们的
is countless failures,
是无数次的失败
and we will definitely
我们也一定会
go on steadfastly.
坚定不移地走下去
Where do I
我提议
propose to go from here?
何去何从
Let's show our hands.
我们举手表决
Comrades, let's show our hands.
同志们 我们举手表决
Those who agree to dissolve the work-study mutual aid society raise their hands.
同意解散工读互助社的 举手
Okay, the results are in.
好 结果出来了
I declare
我宣布
the first experimental group of the Beijing work-study mutual aid society
北京工读互助社第一实验小组
dissolved.
解散
Let's clean up.
大家收拾一下吧
"Time flows like water,"
光阴似流水
"Soon we shall depart from school,"
不一会 课毕放学归
"We will ponder for a while"
我们仔细想一会
"to understand today's homework,"
今天功课明白未
"Have we ever gone against our teacher?"
老师讲的话可曾有违背
"Parents want children to come home,"
父母望儿归
"We should not wander on the road"
我们一路莫徘徊
"of leading the country's future and the world"
将来治国平天下
"which depends on our generation,"
全靠吾辈
"Everybody, let's work hard!"
大家努力呀
"See you again tomorrow, classmates."
同学们 明天再会
"Time flows like water,"
光阴似流水
"Soon we shall depart from school,"
不一会 课毕放学归
"We will ponder for a while"
我们仔细想一会
"to understand today's homework,"
今天功课明白未
"Have we ever gone against our teacher?"
老师讲的话可曾有违背
"Parents want children to come home,"
父母望儿归
"We should not wander on the road"
我们一路莫徘徊
"of leading the country's future and the world"
将来治国平天下
"which depends on our generation,"
全靠吾辈
"Everybody, let's work hard!"
大家努力呀
"See you again tomorrow, classmates."
同学们 明天再会
Comrades!
同志们
See you again tomorrow!
明天 再会
This plaque has been hanging for two months.
这匾挂了两个月
Still taking it off.
还是摘下来了
Guo, put it here.
老郭 放这边
Mr. Cai.
蔡先生
Gentlemen are here.
各位先生都来了
Here, steamed buns.
来 包子蒸好了
There are no Anhui dishes today.
今天也没有什么徽菜
No Shandong cuisine.
没有什么鲁菜
Only dumplings.
只有包子
Okay, just dumplings.
好 就包子
What about today?
那咱们今天呢
Let's have a chat with these dumplings.
就就着这个包子来聊一聊
Alright?
好不好
Okay, sit down.
好 坐下
Yu Xiusong, you start first.
俞社委 你先发个头
Everybody sit down.
大家坐
Sit down.
坐下 坐下
Dear Mr. Cai.
尊敬的蔡先生
[Cai Yuanpei, styled Jiemin, President of Peking University]
[蔡元培 字 孑民 北京大学校长]
Dear mentors.
尊敬的各位导师
Dear ladies.
各位夫人
Dear comrades.
各位同志
Today
今天对于我们
was supposed to be a sad day for the members
工读互助社的成员来说
of our work-study mutual aid society.
本来是个悲伤的日子
But because of Mr. Cai
可是由于蔡先生
and the arrival of the mentors,
和各位导师的到来
it has become a memorable day again.
它又变成了一个值得纪念的日子
[Lu Xun, Civil servant under the Ministry of Education]
[鲁迅 教育部佥事]
More than two months ago,
两个多月前
with the support and sponsorship of our mentors,
我们在各位导师的支持和赞助下
we started this work-study mutual aid society
创办了这个工读互助社
and our members
我们这个互助社的成员
are all
都是清一色
young men and women around 20 years old.
二十罗左右的男女青年
This is our first step towards life
这是我们迈向人生的第一步
is also the experience and pursuit
也是我们追求理想生活的
of our ideal life.
体验与追寻
We persisted for more than two months.
我们坚持了两个多月
We failed today.
今天我们失败了
We can't thank our mentors enough
我们对各位导师的支持和教悔
for their support and teaching.
无以为报
Let's ask Mr. Cai to give us a lecture.
下面 请蔡先生给我们做训示
Please sit down.
你请坐
I'm sorry.
抱歉得很
There's been a lot going on at school these months.
这几个月来学校事情很多
I didn't care
我也就没顾得上
about the work-study mutual aid society.
工读互助社这一块
I was surprised to hear
听说要解散了
that it was going to be disbanded.
我这心里还是很吃惊的
I ran to see everyone.
就赶紧跑过来看望大家
I am concerned about the theory of mutual aid
我呢是关注互助论
and you are practicing it
而你们用自己的实际行动
with your own actions.
在践行着互助论
So you all are a lot better than me,
因此你们比我强
although in front of you,
在你们的面前
I am the head of a school.
我尽管是一校之长
In this respect,
在这个方面
I want to learn from you.
我要向你们学习
I salute you young people
我对你们这些年轻人的勇敢行为
for your bravery.
表示敬意
I believe
我相信
your practice and experiment of mutual aid theory today
你们今天对互助论的实践和试验
will become a valuable asset in your life.
必将成为你们人生中的宝贵财富
I thank you sir for your approval and encouragement.
我感谢先生的认同和鼓励
In the past two months,
这两个月来
we have tried our best
我们竭尽全力做了一切
to do everything we can.
我们能做的事情
The experiment failed
虽然这个实验失败了
but we have a clear conscience.
但是我们问心无愧
Today I would like to take this opportunity
今天借着这个机会
to ask the gentlemen.
我想请教几位先生
In your opinion
在你们看来
what is the root cause
这个互助社失败的根源
of the failure of this mutual aid society?
究竟是什么
You're good.
你不错嘛
Failure without discouragement.
失败了而不气馁
Keep a clear head and actively look for reasons.
保持清醒的头脑积极地寻找原因
In order to have the courage to move forward in the future
为的是将来有勇气地往前走
Isn't it?
是吗
Yes.
是
Good. Student Yannian, let me ask you first.
好 延年同学 我先问你
What do you think is the root of this failure?
你认为这次失败的根源是什么呢
I think there must be more than one reason.
我觉得原因肯定不止一个
But perhaps the most important thing is
但是最重要的
that we don't understand
可能是我们对
the theory and practice of mutual aid enough,
互助论的理论和方法领会得不够
by either missing the point
不得要领
or deviating from it.
或者有所偏差
What do you all think?
你们认为呢
I think there are many disputes.
我看争执还不少
Brother Zhongfu, I suggest opening another column
仲甫兄 我建议再开一个栏目
for everyone
让大家好好地
to properly summarize the experience and lessons learned.
总结一下经验和教训
What do you think?
你看呢
Okay, Master Cai is right.
好 蔡公说得对
Then, on behalf of "New Youth",
那我这就代表《新青年》
I'll formally ask the members for a draft.
正式地向各位社员们约稿了
You have done a very useful experiment
你们为中国青年
for the youth of China.
做了一件非常有益的试验
Your summary and experience
你们的总结和体会
is the most convincing.
是最具说服力的
At the same time,
同时呢
I also want to ask Shouchang and Shizhi to write the manuscript.
我也要请守常 适之来写稿
Shizhi,
适之
you tell everyone about your feelings.
你跟大家聊聊 说说你的感受
I have studied work-study programmes.
对于工读我是研究过的
In the United States,
在美国啊
tens of thousands of people live a work-study life.
有好几万人过着工读的生活
But for young people in the United States
可是对于美国的年轻人来说
they are not interested in the work-study program.
他们对于工读这件事情
They feel it is an extremely normal
他们觉得是极正常
and free choice.
极自由的选择
It's not a great new life.
不是什么了不得的新生活
But in China,
可是在中国
it is an amazing thing.
它就是一件了不起的事情
As for us,
至于说我们
why did it fail after a few months?
为什么办了几个月就失败了
There are many reasons.
原因有很多
I saw at least one of them.
至少有一条我就看到了
It was not well planned.
计划不够周全
Working more and studying less.
工的多 读的少
The result?
结果呢
It's just that working is much more bitter.
就是做工的苦趣多了
The fun of studying is a little less.
读书的乐趣少了那么一点
Work-study.
工读
Work. Study.
工 读
What is the relationship between the two?
二者之间有什么样的关系
Have you thought about it?
大家想过没有
The purpose of working is to study.
做工的目的就是为了读书
And think about it.
而大家想一想
Have we read many books in the past two months?
我们这两个月有没有读很多书
Do you have time to read?
有没有时间去看书
Are there students
是不是有的同学
who have read less books than before
在这两个多月当中
in the past two months?
读的书比以前还少了呢
There are.
有吧
So, our mutual aid society
所以 咱们互助社
has reversed the original intention.
把本未给颠倒了
How can it be successful?
焉有成功之理呢
It's not, Shizhi.
不是 适之啊
You are a well-fed man, but you don't know if a hungry man is hungry.
你这是饱汉子不知饿汉子饥呀
See?
看见没有
This plaque has just been taken off.
这块扁刚刚摘下来
Lu Xun writes very well.
鲁迅先生写得很好
To sweat on one's forehead,
宁流额上汗
than stain blood on one's hands.
毋染手中血
Why do students do this experiment?
同学们做这个实验是为什么
In order to rely on their own labor.
为的就是凭借自己的劳动
To maintain their studies.
去维持学业
Right?
对吧
So what's wrong with the students?
那么同学们有什么错
I don't think there's anything wrong with it.
我觉得没有什么错嘛
Shizhi, what you just said.
适之 你刚才说的
With no work, how can I finish my studies?
不工作那怎么完成学业呢
And with what to eat?
又凭什么吃饭呢
Aren't you throwing cold water on everyone?
你这不是给大伙泼冷水吗
Why am I pouring cold water on it?
我怎么在泼冷水呢
Shouchang, since you say so,
守常 既然你这么说
I'd like to hear your thoughts.
我倒想听听你的想法
My opinion is this:
我的看法是这样的啊
to find the root of the failure of our mutual aid society,
要找着我们互助社失败的根源
first of all, we must recognize clearly
首先先要认清楚
whether it is due to internal
究竟是内因所致
or external causes.
还是外因所致
Yannian, have you considered
延年 你们有没有考虑过
the deeper reason?
更深层次的原因
What do you mean?
您的意思是
I mean, have you ever thought about
我的意思是 你们有没有想过
there is something wrong with the theory of mutual aid itself.
互助论这个理论本身出了问题
You mean there is something wrong with the theory of mutual aid itself?
您是说互助论本身有问题
Unscientific.
不科学
I think at least everyone
我觉得起码大伙
can study this problem.
可以研究这个问题
There are two points.
有两点啊
First,
第一点
is the theory of mutual aid
互助论究竟是不是
a scientific theory?
一个科学的理论
Second,
第二点
is it suitable for China?
它究竟适不适合中国
So what's your conclusion?
那您的结论是什么
I think the success of the October Revolution in Russia
我认为 俄国十月革命的成功
is more suitable for China than the theory of mutual aid.
比互助论更适合我们中国
Shouchang, you digress.
守常 你跑题了啊
I think you are taking this opportunity
我认为你是在借此机会
to promote the October Revolution
宣扬十月革命
On this occasion,
在这个场合
it's not appropriate to talk about these things.
不大适合谈论这些东西
I disagree with you.
我不赞同你的说法
It's not, Shizhi.
不是 适之啊
I didn't take the opportunity to promote the October Revolution.
我不是借机宣传十月革命
I'm just offering a new idea
我只是提供一个新的思想
for everyone to discuss.
供大家来讨论
You don't mention the October Revolution.
你不能一提十月革命
You're against it, right?
你就心怀抵触 对吧
There is no objection.
没有抵触啊
No, then how is it not contradictory?
不是 那怎么不是抵触呢
On such an occasion today-
今天这样一个场合
Shizhi, I think it just contradicts-
适之 我觉得就是抵触
All right, all right, all right.
好了好了好了
I have my opinion.
我有我的观点
Students have their own opinions.
同学们有同学们的观点
Brother Shouchang, Professor Shizhi.
守常兄 适之教授
What you two said makes sense to me.
你们两个人说的我看都有道理
Just don't discuss it here today.
只不过今天在此就不要讨论了
Let's find a place another day
改天我们找一个地方
to have a good discussion.
好好地讨论一下
Alright.
好
Come on.
来
Failure teaches success.
失败乃成功之母
The end is the beginning.
结束即是开始
Our task today
我们今天的任务
is to finish these buns.
就是要把这些包子吃完
Not just steamed buns
不光是包子
but also the pickles and garlic here all eaten,
包括这里的咸菜和大蒜通通吃光
until there is not a grain left in the clean canteen.
俭洁食堂一粒不剩
Come on.
来来来
Here.
来
Brother Shouchang, I really didn't object.
守常兄 我真的没有抵触
You two, eat the buns.
二位吃包子吧
I'm eating, Mr. Cai.
吃着呢 蔡先生
Do you really agree
你真的同意
to let them both go back to Shanghai?
让他们俩再回上海呀
Didn't you also read Liu Wenyao's letter?
那柳文耀的来信你不是也看了吗
It said that the places for work-study in France
说是留法勤工俭学的名额
were allocated to the French class of Aurora University,
分给了震旦学校的法文班
and that the places in the French language training center in Beijing were finished.
北京法文进修馆的名额分配完了
If they want to go to France,
延年他们要想去法国
they have to go back to Shanghai to finish their studies
就必须要回上海完成学业
Obviously, he designed this in the morning.
这显然是他一早就设计好了的
These two boys really want
这两个小子一门心思
to go to France to work and study.
想去法国勤工俭学
Then let them go back to Shanghai.
那只能让他们回上海吧
The mutual aid society failed.
这互助社失败了
It hit them both particularly hard.
对他们俩打击特别大
Especially Yannian.
尤其是延年
The child has a heavy heart.
这孩子心重
I'm afraid he can't bear it.
我真怕他担不住
These two children are now taking risks and struggling.
这两个孩子如今正是冒险苦斗
An indomitable time.
横厉无前的年华
In particular, they needs hardship to be tempered.
尤其需要艰难困苦加以砥砺
Don't worry.
你放心
They have an old man like me.
有我这样的老子
Will these two kids be demoralized?
这两个伢子岂会颓丧沉沦
Yannian, Qiaonian.
延年 乔年
Come out. I want to talk to you.
出来 我来跟你们聊聊
Dad,
爸
you have to lecture again.
您又要训话
No, I'm just talking to you.
不训话 就是跟你们聊聊
You are going to Shanghai.
你们这就要去上海了
Go get a chair and sit down.
你们去拿个凳子坐
I lifted up my head and said I was tired.
我仰着头说也累
Yannian,
延年
the mutual aid experiment failed.
互助社试验失败了
I want to ask you, are you still so convinced
我想问你 你还那么坚信
of the theory of anarchism?
无政府主义的理论吗
Will you be angry if I say I firmly believe in it?
如果我说坚信 您会生气吗
I won't.
不会
Truth?
真话
Why?
为什么
Because I saw your reflection.
因为我看见了你的反思
If you have reflection, you will not be blind.
有反思就不会盲目
I believe
我相信
you will surely find a right way.
你一定会找到一条正确的路
I am willing to give you time.
我愿意给你时间
I'm willing to go looking for it with you.
我也愿意跟你们一起去寻找
Thank you.
谢谢
Dad, I thought you were going to force us again
爸 我还以为您又要逼着我们
to study the October Revolution.
研究十月革命呢
I'm not forcing you,
不是逼着你们
just suggesting.
只是建议
Rest assured,
您放心
we will stick to the theory of mutual aid,
虽然我们坚守互助论
but we will
但是我们一定会
learn from different perspectives.
多方面地涉猎学习
Good.
好
During my stay in Beijing,
在北京这段时间
I have seen your growth with my own eyes.
我亲眼看见了你们的成长
To tell the truth,
说实话
as a father, I am very pleased.
作为一个父亲 我很欣慰
We also have a new understanding of you.
我们对您也有新的认识
Your thoughts have also benefited me and Qiaonian a lot.
您的思想也让我跟乔年受益匪浅
But there's just one thing.
但就是有一点
What?
什么
It's nothing.
没什么
We hope you will change
我们希望您把您那种
your style and habits,
大家长的作风和习惯改一改
especially when you treat your colleagues.
特别是在您对待自己同人的时候
That would hurt them too much.
那样对他们伤害太大了
I'll fry some peanuts for you.
那个 我给你们炒点花生
Take it back to eat on the road.
回头带在路上吃
What are you doing?
你干吗
The two children are going to Shanghai.
这两个孩子要去上海了
Can't I fry peanuts for them?
我给他们炒花生不行吗
Go and get some pumpkin seeds.
去 把那个南瓜子拿过来一些
Why?
干吗
When Qiaonian was a child, he liked fried peanuts.
小时候乔年喜欢吃炒花生
Yannian likes to eat pumpkin seeds.
延年就喜欢吃南瓜子
Pumpkin seeds and peanuts are cooked differently.
南瓜子和花生受热程度不一样
You'll fry it if you stir it up.
你这混着炒会炒煳的
When Yannian was young,
延年小时候
he liked to eat fried pumpkin seeds.
就喜欢吃炒煳的南瓜子
You don't know this?
这个你不知道
Think of this one?
觉得这篇吧
It's a bit repetitive with what we published in the last issue.
和咱们上一期刊登的有点重复
So I suggest
所以我建议
this-
这
Shouchang, Zhongfu.
守常 仲甫
Shizhi.
适之
Tell you some good news.
告诉你们一个好消息
My teacher, Mr. Dewey, has decided
我的老师杜威先生已经决定
to come to China from Japan on the 27th to give lectures.
二十七号从日本启程来华讲学
I'm here to ask for leave.
我是来向您告假的
I want to meet my teacher in Shanghai.
我想到上海接我的老师
I see you're happy.
看把你高兴的
The 27th is still a long way off.
二十七号还早着呢
Besides, at that time,
再说那个时候
I should also step down as dean of liberal arts.
我这文科学长也该卸任了
You don't have to ask me for leave.
你也不用跟我请假
What are you talking about?
你说什么话呢
You've always been my dean.
什么时候您都是我的学长啊
Dewey's coming to China is a good thing.
这杜威来华是好事情
Although I don't fully agree with his
虽然我不完全赞同他那个
experimental viewpoint.
实验主义观点
But his pragmatic ideas
但是他那个务实的理念
are still refreshing.
还是让人耳目一新的
Shizhi,
适之
you, Jiang Menglin, and Tao Xingzhi
你跟那个蒋梦麟还有陶行知
are his disciples.
都是他弟子
You guys plan well.
你们好好谋划一下
Let him stay in China for a few more days.
争让他在中国多待一些日子
A couple more.
多讲几次
Now, Chinese people
趁着现在国人
have a good feeling for the United States and Wilson.
对美国和威尔逊还有好感
I told you,
我跟你说
we've been planning Mr. Dewey's trip
为了安排杜威先生的行程
for more than a month.
我们已经筹划了一个多月了
I hope that my teacher's visit to China
我想通过我的老师这次来华
will create a whirlwind
能够在中国掀起一股
of experimentalism in China.
实验主义的旋风
Because experimentalism is so useful to China,
因为实验主义对中国太有用了
China wants to be strong.
中国想要强大起来
We must learn from the United States in its entirety.
就一定要全盘向美国学习
Shizhi, that's biased.
适之 偏颇了啊
How long has the United States been founded?
美国建国才多长时间
How many years is China's history?
中国有多少年的历史了
The national conditions of the two countries are different.
两国国情不一样
Cultural traditions are different.
文化传统不一样
How can it be compared?
怎么可以相提并论呢
I agree with Shouchang.
我同意守常的观点啊
But today?
不过今天呢
I'd rather hope that the United States
我倒还是寄希望美囯
can help us contain Japan.
能够帮助我们遏制日本
So I wrote an article last month
所以上个月我还写了篇文章
praising this Wilson as a great man.
称赞这个威尔逊是个大好人
You still think so?
你现在还这么认为
Now I call him Big Cannon
现在 我称他是威大炮
Big Cannon? What do you mean?
威大炮 什么意思
He fired a gun.
他放空炮呗
It's not like you didn't read
他那十四条和平建议
his fourteen peace proposals
你又不是没看
Which one is not an empty gun?
哪条不是放空炮
Let me see.
我看啊
China pins Shandong problem on him.
中国把山东问题寄托在他身上
Concerning.
悬
I think you two are too pessimistic.
我觉得你们俩太悲观了
I hope the facts don't make us pessimistic.
但愿事实不要让我们悲观
Mr. Cai.
蔡先生
Everyone's here.
都在这儿呢
Sir.
先生
Mr. Cai.
蔡先生
Come on, sit down.
来快请坐
Please sit down.
您请坐
I have something to tell you three.
我有件事情要跟三位说一下
Wang Daxie told me today.
今天汪大燮告诉我
He said that the Paris Peace Conference was not going well.
他说巴黎和会的情况不妙
Japan which presented two documents
日本呢它在巴黎和会上
at the Paris Peace Conference.
摆出了两个文件
One is, Duan Qirui,
一个呢是段祺瑞
in order to borrow money from the Japanese,
为了向日本人借钱
admitted that Japan
他承认了日本可以在山东
could inherit all the German rights and interests in Shandong
继承德国的所有权益的
under a secret treaty.
这么一个密约
What about the second one?
第二一个呢
It's Britain, France and other countries
就是英法等国呀
also acquiesced in such a treaty.
也默认了这么一个条约
So now the Japanese are trying to force
所以现在日本人要拿着这两个文件
the Americans into submission with these two documents.
逼美国人就范
So,
那这么说
Wilson doesn't want this justice either.
这威尔逊他的公理也不要了
Wang Daxie told me
汪大燮告诉我
the United States has always shared interests.
美国呢向来是利益均沾
He must resist this request from Japan.
他呢肯定要抵制日本的这个要求
But to what extent can it be resisted?
但是能抵制到什么程度
It's hard to say.
这就不好说了
Then Britain, France and Italy are unreliable.
那英法意也靠不住了
The key is to look at this requirement of the United States for Japan.
关键是看美国对日本的这个要求
What kind of plan will it come up with?
它会拿出什么样的方案来
It's over.
完了
Unreliable.
靠不住
Who is unreliable?
谁靠不住
I think Wilson is a gentleman.
我觉得威尔逊是君子
Discussion is reliable.
说话是靠谱的
Let's just leave it at that.
我们就不管这些了
Now we have to take care of ourselves.
我们现在要管管我们自己
If something really big like this happens,
真要出了这样的大事
What will we do at Peking University?
我们北大怎么办
Now Peking University is famous.
现在北大已经出了名了
Zhongfu and Shouchang as well.
仲甫也好 守常也好
You're all on the police department's list.
都上了警察厅的名单
More importantly, our students don't attend classes.
更重要的是我们的学生不上课
This heart can't be held back.
这个人心都拢不住
It's really the Paris Peace Conference that's going to go wrong.
真正是巴黎和会要出了状况
That's bound to happen in China.
那国内肯定是要出大事的
So I said,
所以我说
brother Zhongfu, we have to plan ahead.
仲甫兄手 我们得未雨绸缪才是啊
Mr. Cai,
蔡先生
I think the current situation
我倒觉得当前的形势
is a good situation.
是一个好的形势
Everyone's patriotic enthusiasm
大家的爱国热情
is all mobilized.
都已经调动起来了
We just take advantage of the situation.
我们正好因势利导
Mr. Cai, I don't think we can mess around.
蔡先生 我觉得不能乱
This is the principle of guiding the situation according to the situation.
这才是我们因势利导的原则
Zhongfu, why don't you talk?
仲甫 你怎么不说话呢
I have to think about it.
我得想想
You really have to think about it this time.
你这次真得好好想想
You can't go to extremes anymore.
不能再走极端了啊
No, Shizhi, how come you've been spending so much time lately
不 适之 最近你怎么一天到晚
always talking about extremes?
总是把极端挂在嘴上啊
You don't pour cold water on everyone.
你不给大家泼冷水
Do you feel uncomfortable?
你心里不舒服吗
I didn't mean that.
我不是那个意思
I'm just saying what I think.
我只是把我的想法说出来而已
No offense, brother Zhongfu.
没有冒犯你的意思 仲甫兄
I'm hungry. I'll be back to eat.
我饿了 回去吃饭
Is he angry?
他是生气了吗
Isn't that what it is?
那这样不就是
Feudalism has grown up?
封建主义大家长了吗
Mr. Cai,
这个蔡先生
I'm- I'm also hungry.
我也 我也饿了
I- I- I-
我 我 我
I'm hungry. Me too.
我饿了 我也
I also want to go eat.
我也去吃饭了
Yes, yes.
是是
Shouchang.
守常
Everyone's hungry. Everyone's hungry.
都饿了 都饿了 都饿了
Mr. Cai, can't I tell the truth?
蔡先生 我就不能说说实话吗
I just gestured to you, and you-
我刚才给你打手势你
Alright. Alright.
好了好了
Come on.
来来来
I'll take you to the scholar's residence for dinner.
我带你到学士居去吃饭
Come on, my treat.
来 我请客
You don't know.
你不知道
All countries are good.
国家都好